<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Rebeja</title><link>https://blog.rebeja.eu/</link><description>Single threaded stories.</description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" href="https://blog.rebeja.eu/rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2018 &lt;a href="mailto:petru.rebeja@gmail.com"&gt;Petru Rebeja&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Nov 2018 15:51:18 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Using enums in C#</title><link>https://blog.rebeja.eu/posts/using-enums-in-c-sharp/</link><dc:creator>Petru Rebeja</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Recently Steve Smith posted an article named &lt;a href="http://ardalis.com/enum-alternatives-in-c"&gt;Enum Alternatives in C#&lt;/a&gt; where he points out that &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/sbbt4032.aspx"&gt;C# enums&lt;/a&gt; are nothing more than
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
simple value-type flags that provide very minimal protection from invalid values and no behavior
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In the same article he mentiones &lt;a href="http://blog.falafel.com/introducing-type-safe-enum-pattern/"&gt;type safe enum pattern&lt;/a&gt; as a better alternative to enums due to type safety. As a conclusion, Steve suggests that instead of using and declaring enums in the classical way
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public enum WeekDay
{
    Monday,
    Tuesday,
    Wednesday,
    Thursday,
    Friday,
    Saturday,
    Sunday
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
we should declare them in a &lt;code&gt;type safe&lt;/code&gt; manner like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class WeekDay
{
    public static WeekDay Monday = new WeekDay(0, Resources.Monday);
    public static WeekDay Tuesday = new WeekDay(1, Resources.Tuesday);
    public static WeekDay Wednesday = new WeekDay(2, Resources.Wednesday);
    public static WeekDay Thursday = new WeekDay(3, Resources.Thursday);
    public static WeekDay Friday = new WeekDay(4, Resources.Friday);
    public static WeekDay Saturday = new WeekDay(5, Resources.Saturday);
    public static WeekDay Sunday = new WeekDay(6, Resources.Sunday);

    private WeekDay(int value, string name)
    {
	Value = value;
	Name = name;
    }

    public int Value { get; private set; }
    public string Name { get; private set; }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This way the &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/06tc147t.aspx"&gt;&lt;code&gt;switch&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; we all know and love (&lt;b&gt;not&lt;/b&gt;) on the values of &lt;code&gt;WeekDay&lt;/code&gt; will remain the same. Although this is a very elegant way of solving the issue of someone calling &lt;code&gt;themeSelector.GetTheme((WeekDay)13)&lt;/code&gt; without getting an error from the compiler there are some issues with &lt;code&gt;type safe enums&lt;/code&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First of all, &lt;code&gt;type safe enums&lt;/code&gt; are &lt;code&gt;nullable&lt;/code&gt; which means that now we can call &lt;code&gt;themeSelector.GetTheme(null)&lt;/code&gt; and that would be a valid call which will most probably throw a &lt;code&gt;NullReferenceException&lt;/code&gt; when executed.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Second, &lt;code&gt;type safe enums&lt;/code&gt; cannot represent &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.flagsattribute(v=vs.110).aspx#Anchor_7"&gt;flags&lt;/a&gt; easily; they &lt;i&gt;can&lt;/i&gt; by enumerating all possible values but that may not be an easy task for large &lt;code&gt;enums&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
However, the problems the article refers to are not in the lack of compiler checks for valid &lt;code&gt;enum&lt;/code&gt; values but rather how the &lt;code&gt;enum&lt;/code&gt; values are used.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;Displaying &lt;code&gt;enums&lt;/code&gt; in UI elements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let's look at the simplest problem Steve mentiones - displaying &lt;code&gt;enum&lt;/code&gt; values in the UI. Indeed using the &lt;code&gt;DescriptionAttribute&lt;/code&gt; is not the best solution you can have.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The biggest grudge &lt;b&gt;I&lt;/b&gt; have with &lt;code&gt;DescriptionAttribute&lt;/code&gt; is that it doesn't play nice with applications that have to support multiple languages. However, for the past few years (basically since &lt;code&gt;extension methods&lt;/code&gt; were added to .NET Framework) I've taken another approach on displaying &lt;code&gt;enum&lt;/code&gt; values in the UI.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The idea behind this is simple - build a &lt;code&gt;Dictionary&amp;lt;TEnum, string&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; where the keys are &lt;code&gt;enum&lt;/code&gt; values and values are localized strings taken from a resource file and bind the results to whatever control is used to display the &lt;code&gt;enum&lt;/code&gt;. And for that I use a single &lt;code&gt;extension method&lt;/code&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public static class EnumUtils
{
    public static Dictionary&amp;lt;T, string&amp;gt; GetLocalizedEnumValues&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;(this ResourceManager resourceManager)
    {
	return Enum.GetValues(typeof(T))
	    .Cast&amp;lt;T&amp;gt;()
	    .Select(val =&amp;gt; new { Value = val, Text = resourceManager.GetString(val.ToString()) })
	    .ToDictionary(kvp =&amp;gt; kvp.Value, kvp =&amp;gt; kvp.Text);
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, this method relies on a convention that the resource file must have entries for each &lt;code&gt;enum&lt;/code&gt; value in order for it to work but when working with applications that support multiple languages there is seldom a case when something that needs to be displayed in the UI is not localized.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And now let's look at how this method can be used to localize &lt;code&gt;enum&lt;/code&gt; values; as the example platform let's consider &lt;code&gt;ASP.NET MVC&lt;/code&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class ThemeController : Controller
{
    public ActionResult Index()
    {
	var viewModel = new ThemeViewModel
	{
	    WeekDays = Resources.ResourceManager.GetLocalizedEnumValues&amp;lt;WeekDay&amp;gt;()
		.Select(kvp =&amp;gt; new SelectListItem { Value = kvp.Key, Text = kvp.Value})
	};
	return View(viewModel);
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Granted, it's more work to do in order to display &lt;code&gt;enums&lt;/code&gt; like this but there are advantages:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;No magic strings&lt;/b&gt; are involved compared to using &lt;code&gt;DescriptionAttribute&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have to do &lt;b&gt;less repetitive work&lt;/b&gt;. If you declare your &lt;code&gt;enum&lt;/code&gt; in a &lt;code&gt;type safe&lt;/code&gt; manner you'll have the tedious task of pairing each &lt;code&gt;enum&lt;/code&gt; value with its (localized) description by hand; &lt;code&gt;GetlocalizedEnumValues&lt;/code&gt; method will do that automatically for all enums which have entries in the resources file.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;Use defensive coding in &lt;code&gt;switch&lt;/code&gt; statements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, let's address the bigger issue when dealing with &lt;code&gt;enums&lt;/code&gt;, namely calling (in our case) &lt;code&gt;themeSelector.GetTheme((WeekDay)13)&lt;/code&gt;. The problem here is that a lot of developers don't use defensive programming when dealing with &lt;code&gt;enums&lt;/code&gt; (or at all).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's consider how our &lt;code&gt;GetTheme&lt;/code&gt; method would look like in a non-defensive style and to emphasize things let's look at the worst-case scenario:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class ThemeSelector
{
    public Theme GetTheme(WeekDay weekDay)
    {
	switch(weekDay)
	    case WeekDay.Monday:
		return new Theme { Playlist = "Monday mood" };
	    case WeekDay.Tuesday:
		return new Theme { Playlist = "Four more days to Friday" };
	    case WeekDay.Wednesday:
		return new Theme { Playlist = "It's hump day already!" };
	    case WeekDay.Thursday:
		return new Theme { Playlist = "One more day!" };
	    case WeekDay.Friday:
		return new Theme { Playlist = "Friday margueritas!" };
	    case WeekDay.Saturday:
		return new Theme { Playlist = "Go away hangover!" };
	    case WeekDay.Sunday:
	    default: // BAD!!!
		return new Theme { Playlist = "There's still time to party!" };
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
See the problem there? The developer &lt;b&gt;assumes that the method will always receive a valid value&lt;/b&gt; thus he/she links the &lt;code&gt;default&lt;/code&gt; case with an existing label instead of checking the value.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The simplest fix for this is below:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class ThemeSelector
{
    public Theme GetTheme(WeekDay weekDay)
    {
	switch(weekDay)
	    case WeekDay.Monday:
		return new Theme { Playlist = "Monday mood" };
	    case WeekDay.Tuesday:
		return new Theme { Playlist = "Four more days to Friday" };
	    case WeekDay.Wednesday:
		return new Theme { Playlist = "It's hump day already!" };
	    case WeekDay.Thursday:
		return new Theme { Playlist = "One more day!" };
	    case WeekDay.Friday:
		return new Theme { Playlist = "Friday margueritas!" };
	    case WeekDay.Saturday:
		return new Theme { Playlist = "Go away hangover!" };
	    case WeekDay.Sunday:
		return new Theme { Playlist = "There's still time to party!" };
	    default:
		throw new ArgumentException("Invalid value for WeekDay enum.");
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Throwing the &lt;code&gt;ArgumentException&lt;/code&gt; when receiving an invalid value will crash the application but this crash gives us at least two benefits:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The application behavior becomes predictable: &lt;code&gt;GetTheme&lt;/code&gt; method will either return a valid &lt;code&gt;Theme&lt;/code&gt; or will throw an error
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It makes debugging &lt;b&gt;a lot&lt;/b&gt; easier; you know the point of failure, you know the reason and you have the full stack trace. When the application crashes twenty steps after receiving the invalid value there are a lot more unknows to &lt;b&gt;why&lt;/b&gt; the application crashed and it may be harder to reproduce the problem.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-3"&gt;Use specialzed &lt;code&gt;builders&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code&gt;switch&lt;/code&gt; statements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
However, the best way to use &lt;code&gt;switch&lt;/code&gt; statements is to avoid it altoghether. Why? Mainly because &lt;code&gt;switch&lt;/code&gt; statements are the main violators of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open/closed_principle"&gt;Open/Closed Principle&lt;/a&gt; i.e.every time a new member of the enum is added, every &lt;code&gt;switch&lt;/code&gt; on that enum values needs to be changed in order to accomodate the new member (except for the cases that use the &lt;code&gt;default&lt;/code&gt; label).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In such cases I prefer to use something that I call &lt;code&gt;specialized builders&lt;/code&gt; to avoid the switch statement.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The ideea is simple: the logic behind each label of the &lt;code&gt;switch&lt;/code&gt; statement is refactored into a separate class which implements a common interface for all the labels. The same interface exposes a property of the enum type which tells the clients of the interface which enum value it can process. The client code receives as a dependency a collection of such instances and instead of a switch statement it just iterates through the collection to find the suitable instance.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's exemplify using our scenario; instead of having the &lt;code&gt;switch&lt;/code&gt; statement inside the &lt;code&gt;GetTheme&lt;/code&gt; method from the previous example, let's refactor each labels logic into a separate class. But before that, let's define an interface that will be implemented by all the classes.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since the switch is used to build instances of &lt;code&gt;Theme&lt;/code&gt; class, let's call the interface &lt;code&gt;IThemeBuilder&lt;/code&gt;; here is it's definition:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public interface IThemeBuilder
{
    WeekDay WeekDay { get; }

    Theme BuildTheme();
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now an implementation of this interface for &lt;code&gt;WeekDay.Monday&lt;/code&gt; would look like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class MondayThemeBuilder
{
    public WeekDay WeekDay
    {
	get { return WeekDay.Monday; }
    }

    public Theme BuildTheme()
    {
	return new Theme { Playlist = "Monday mood" };
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With all the implementations in place, all it remains to do is to register the implementations of &lt;code&gt;IThemeBuilder&lt;/code&gt; interface in the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dependency_injection"&gt;DI&lt;/a&gt; container and inject them into the &lt;code&gt;ThemeSelector&lt;/code&gt; class. The &lt;code&gt;GetTheme&lt;/code&gt; method now becomes an iteration to find a suitable &lt;code&gt;builder&lt;/code&gt; for the argument received. If no such instance is found, an exception is thrown to signal the error.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class ThemeSelector
{
    private readonly IEnumerable&amp;lt;ThemeBuilder&amp;gt; builders;

    public ThemeSelector(IEnumerable&amp;lt;IThemeBuilder&amp;gt; themeBuilders)
    {
	builders = themeBuilders;
    }

    public Theme GetTheme(WeekDay weekDay)
    {
	var builder = builders.SingleOrDefault(b =&amp;gt; b.WeekDay == weekDay);
	if( builder == null)
	    throw new ArgumentException(String.Format("Invalid value '{0}' received for week day.", weekDay));
	return builder.BuildTheme();
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now everytime a new member needs to be added to &lt;code&gt;WeekDay&lt;/code&gt; enum, although not the case here, there are at most three changes to make to accomodate the new value:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the new value to the &lt;code&gt;enum&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a new class that will implement &lt;code&gt;IThemeBuilder&lt;/code&gt; for the new value
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Register the new class in the &lt;code&gt;DI container&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Depending on which &lt;code&gt;dependency injection&lt;/code&gt; library you use, there may be no change required for registering the new class in the container.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-4"&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The main conclusion of the article is that &lt;b&gt;&lt;code&gt;enums&lt;/code&gt; aren't bad they're just improperly used&lt;/b&gt;. Sometimes creating a thick class to represent &lt;code&gt;type safe enums&lt;/code&gt; may be suitable for your scenario but most of the time it's not worth the effort. Instead, you should concentrate more on the places in code where the &lt;code&gt;enum&lt;/code&gt; is used to make them safer, more clean and elegant.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>c#</category><category>enums</category><category>SOLID</category><guid>https://blog.rebeja.eu/posts/using-enums-in-c-sharp/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2016 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Abstraction is not a principle of Object Oriented Programming</title><link>https://blog.rebeja.eu/posts/abstraction-is-not-a-principle-of-object-oriented-programming/</link><dc:creator>Petru Rebeja</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;code&gt;Abstraction&lt;/code&gt; is a core concept in programming and not a principle that is &lt;b&gt;solely&lt;/b&gt; applicable in OOP, because &lt;b&gt;programming is all about dealing with an abstract representation of the business model (application space)&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;Abstraction is an overall programming principle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are a lot of articles saying that OOP has four principles:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Encapsulation&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Inheritance&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Polymorphism&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Abstraction&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But if we do a web searh for &lt;i&gt;what is abstraction?&lt;/i&gt; we get more or less the same definition as the one from &lt;a href="http://whatis.techtarget.com/definition/abstraction"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Abstraction (from the Latin abs, meaning away from and trahere, meaning to draw) is the process of taking away or removing characteristics from something in order to reduce it to a set of essential characteristics.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Although the article defines &lt;code&gt;abstraction&lt;/code&gt; in an OOP context, &lt;i&gt;&lt;code&gt;abstraction&lt;/code&gt; is actually a an overall programming principle&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why? Because programming means modeling entities and interactions of an &lt;i&gt;abstract representation of the business model&lt;/i&gt;. And since there are several programming paradigms all of which are used to represent a set of specific business models all of those paradigms use &lt;code&gt;abstraction&lt;/code&gt; to succeed in that representation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-3"&gt;An example of &lt;code&gt;abstraction&lt;/code&gt; in OOP&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To better clarify what &lt;code&gt;abstraction&lt;/code&gt; is (in OOP) let's consider a trivial example: A &lt;code&gt;StudentRegistrationController&lt;/code&gt; (ASP.NET MVC) needs to save the data from a registration form (&lt;code&gt;Student&lt;/code&gt;) into some sort of database represented by an instance of &lt;code&gt;IStudentDataStore&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For the sake of brevity let's say that &lt;code&gt;IStudentDataStore&lt;/code&gt; interface has the following definition:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public interface IStudentDataStore
{
    void Save(Student student);
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With that in mind, the code for the example above would look like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class Student
{
    public string FirstName { get; set; }

    public string LastName { get; set; }

    public DateTime DateOfBirth { get; set; }

    public Gender Gender { get; set; }

    public string Email { get; set; }

    public string PhoneNumber { get; set; }
}

public class StudentRegistrationController : Controller
{
    public StudentRegistrationController(IStudentDataStore dataStore)
    {
	_dataStore = dataStore;
    }

    public ActionResult Save(Student viewModel)
    {
	// Validation ommited for brevity
	_dataStore.Save(viewModel);
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As we can see from the code the &lt;code&gt;IStudentDataStore&lt;/code&gt; abstracts the details of how &lt;code&gt;Student&lt;/code&gt; data is persisted. The interface doesn't tell whether the data is persisted to a flat file, SQL Database, NoSQL database or other media. As long as we have an implementation of &lt;code&gt;IStudentDataStore&lt;/code&gt; the controller works just fine.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But is this &lt;code&gt;abstraction&lt;/code&gt; technique available &lt;i&gt;only&lt;/i&gt; in OOP paradigm? The answer is &lt;b&gt;no&lt;/b&gt;. The same thing, although in a different form can be used in other paradigms. To demonstrate so, let's use &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lisp_(programming_language)"&gt;lisp&lt;/a&gt; as a programming language and let's see how &lt;i&gt;abstraction&lt;/i&gt; works in a &lt;b&gt;functional programming paradigm&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-4"&gt;The same example of &lt;code&gt;abstraction&lt;/code&gt; in functional programming&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To see how the same thing would be written in a functional style let's first see what are the entities from the previous example and how those entities interact between them:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;StudentRegistrationController&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is the top-most entity
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Has an &lt;code&gt;IStudentDataStore&lt;/code&gt; on which calls the &lt;code&gt;Save&lt;/code&gt; method
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;IStudentDataStore&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defines a contract between the controller and the underlying data store
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Student&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is a data contract, i.e. encapsulates all the properties of a student into a single entity
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Having the above and knowing that in functional programming &lt;i&gt;everything is a function&lt;/i&gt; we replace every &lt;i&gt;entity&lt;/i&gt; with a &lt;i&gt;function&lt;/i&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We'll create a top-level function named &lt;code&gt;save-student&lt;/code&gt;; it will have the following parameters:
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;student-info&lt;/code&gt; -&amp;gt; a hash map containing the data contract
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;persist-func&lt;/code&gt; -&amp;gt; a function that will be called to save the data to a data store
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Another two functions &lt;code&gt;persist-student-info-to-file&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;persist-student-info-in-memory&lt;/code&gt; will encapsulate the logic of persisting data to a data store.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Note that both functions have the same signature. The parameters of these functions represent the data contract.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;persist-student-info-to-file&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;first-name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;last-name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;dob&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;gender&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;email&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;phone&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;;; Writes the info as a new line into the file specified by *database-location*&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;stream&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;open&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="vg"&gt;*database-location*&lt;/span&gt;
	      &lt;span class="ss"&gt;:direction&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;:output&lt;/span&gt;
	      &lt;span class="ss"&gt;:if-exists&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;:append&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;format&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;stream&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"~s|~s|~s|~s|~s|~s"&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="nv"&gt;first-name&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="nv"&gt;last-name&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="nv"&gt;dob&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="nv"&gt;gender&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="nv"&gt;email&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="nv"&gt;phone&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;close&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;stream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;persist-student-info-in-memory&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;first-name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;last-name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;dob&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;gender&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;email&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;phone&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;;; Persists student data into an in-memory data store named *all-students*&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;student-id&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;list-length&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="vg"&gt;*all-students*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;setq&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="vg"&gt;*all-students*&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;append&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="vg"&gt;*all-students*&lt;/span&gt;
	  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;list&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;student-id&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;first-name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;last-name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;dob&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;gender&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;email&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;phone&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)))))&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;save-student&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;student-info&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;persist-func&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;;; Saves student data to a persistent store&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;first-name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;gethash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'first-name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;student-info&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;last-name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;gethash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'last-name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;student-info&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;dob&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;gethash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'date-of-birth&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;student-info&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;gender&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;gethash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'gender&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;student-info&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;email&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;gethash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'email&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;student-info&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;phone&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;gethash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'phone-number&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;student-info&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;funcall&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;persist-func&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;first-name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;last-name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;dob&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;gender&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;email&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;phone&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Having the definitions above we can achieve the same level of abstraction by putting everything together and defining global variables (think of it as poor mans &lt;code&gt;dependency injection&lt;/code&gt;):
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;defparameter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="vg"&gt;*database-location*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"/tmp/students"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;defparameter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="vg"&gt;*student-info*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;make-hash-table&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;progn&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;setf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;gethash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'first-name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="vg"&gt;*student-info*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"John"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;setf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;gethash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'last-name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="vg"&gt;*student-info*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"Doe"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;setf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;gethash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'date-of-birth&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;*student-info&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"2000-05-14"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;setf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;gethash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'email&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="vg"&gt;*student-info*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"john.doe@example.com"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;setf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;gethash&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'phone-number&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="vg"&gt;*student-info*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"1234567981"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;save-student&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="vg"&gt;*student-info*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'persist-student-info-to-file&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Et voilà! We have used &lt;code&gt;abstraction&lt;/code&gt; in a functional style to remove the details of how the data is persisted thus showing that &lt;code&gt;abstraction&lt;/code&gt; isn't a principle applicable only to object oriented programming.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-5" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-5"&gt;Acknowledgments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A big thank you to &lt;a href="https://be.linkedin.com/in/ion-cojocaru-81b5a230"&gt;Ion Cojocaru&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://ro.linkedin.com/in/florin-olariu-38615126"&gt;Florin Olariu&lt;/a&gt; who reviewed this post before publication.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>abstraction</category><category>OOP</category><category>OOP principles</category><guid>https://blog.rebeja.eu/posts/abstraction-is-not-a-principle-of-object-oriented-programming/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 28 Jul 2016 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>FII Practic 2016</title><link>https://blog.rebeja.eu/posts/fii-practic-2016/</link><dc:creator>Petru Rebeja</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;Programming principles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1-1" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sec-1-1"&gt;Chapter I - Object Oriented Programming&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-1"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1-1-1" class="outline-4"&gt;
&lt;h4 id="sec-1-1-1"&gt;Encapsulation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-4" id="text-1-1-1"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Encapsulation_%2528computer_programming%2529"&gt;Encapsulation facilitates bundling of data with the method(s) operating on that data.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To exemplify let's consider the following requirement: &lt;b&gt;As an account holder I want to perform withdrawal and deposit of various amounts from and into my account&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To implement the requirement we consider the following:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An &lt;code&gt;Account&lt;/code&gt; has a &lt;code&gt;Balance&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;code&gt;Withdrawal&lt;/code&gt; is an operation which subtracts the &lt;code&gt;amount&lt;/code&gt; from the &lt;code&gt;Balance&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;code&gt;Deposit&lt;/code&gt; is an operation which adds the &lt;code&gt;amount&lt;/code&gt; to the &lt;code&gt;Balance&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The code below should do it:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class Account
{
    public Money Balance { get; set; }

}

public class Program
{
    static void Main(string[] args)
    {
	var account = new Account();
	// Make a deposit
	account.Balance += 50;
	// Withdraw some cash
	account.Balance -= 100;
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/Houston,_we_have_a_problem"&gt;Houston, we have a problem&lt;/a&gt;. If we let the consumers of our code (in this case &lt;code&gt;Program&lt;/code&gt;) to change the &lt;code&gt;Balance&lt;/code&gt; at will, our system may end up in such funky situations where account holders can withdraw as much money as they want from the ATM without having enough funds.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
    Of course, we need to validate each withdrawal but we can't surround each &lt;code&gt;account.Balance -= amount&lt;/code&gt; with an &lt;code&gt;if(account.Balance &amp;gt; amount)&lt;/code&gt; because it's time consuming, inefficient
and we simply may not have access to the code that uses our class. What we &lt;i&gt;can&lt;/i&gt; do is to &lt;b&gt;encapsulate&lt;/b&gt; the withdrawal and validation into a single operation like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class Account
{
    public Money Balance {get; private set; } // The balance is now read-only

    public Money Withdraw(Money amount)
    {
	if( Balance &amp;lt;= amount)
	{
	    throw new InvalidOperationException("Insufficient funds.");
	}
	this.Balance -= amount;
	return amount;
    }

    public void Deposit(Money money)
    {
	this.Balance += money;
    }
}

public class Program
{
    static void Main(string[] args)
    {
	var account = new Account();
	account.Deposit(50);
	account.Withdraw(100); // =&amp;gt; InvalidOperationException.
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Much better! Now we are in control and we can be sure that &lt;i&gt;every&lt;/i&gt; withdrawal is validated against account balance. As a nice side effect our code gains &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_programming#Readability_of_source_code"&gt;readability&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1-1-2" class="outline-4"&gt;
&lt;h4 id="sec-1-1-2"&gt;Inheritance and Polymorphism&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-4" id="text-1-1-2"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.codeproject.com/Articles/22769/Introduction-to-Object-Oriented-Programming-Concep#Inheritance"&gt;Inheritance is the ability of a new class to acquire the properties of another class.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's look at another requirement:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;As an account holder I can have multiple accounts of various types such as savings account, debit account etc for which different withdrawal fees apply. For a debit account the withdrawal fee is zero; for a savings account the withdrawal fee is 0.5% of the amount withdrawn.&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
From the requirement we can deduct that an &lt;code&gt;Account&lt;/code&gt; can be modeled as a class with two properties - a &lt;code&gt;Balance&lt;/code&gt; and a &lt;code&gt;Type&lt;/code&gt; which can take values from an enumeration.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Also, additional changes to the &lt;code&gt;Withdraw&lt;/code&gt; method should be applied:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each withdrawal calculates and subtracts a fee from the balance
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The check for insufficient funds should also take into the consideration the fee alongside the amount
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Given the above, our code would look like this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public enum AccountType
{
    Debit,
    Savings
}

public class Account
{
    private readonly AccountType _accountType;

    public Account(AccountType accountType)
    {
	_accountType = accountType;
    }

    public AccountType AccountType { get { return _accountType; } }

    public Money Balance { get; private set; }

    public void Deposit(Money money)
    {
	this.Balance += money;
    }

    public Money Withdraw(Money amount)
    {
	var fee = CalculateWithdrawalFee(amount);
	amount = amount + fee;
	if( Balance &amp;lt;= amount)
	{
	    throw new InvalidOperationException("Insufficient funds.");
	}
	this.Balance -= amount;
    }

    private Money CalculateWithdrawalFee(Money amount)
    {
	var margin = _accountType == AccountType.Savings ? 0.5 : 0;
	return amount * margin / 100;
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Everything looks good except the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magic_number_%2528programming%2529"&gt;magic numbers&lt;/a&gt;. Until we get a new requirement:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;As an account holder I can have a credit account with a withdrawal fee of 0.7%&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To accomodate this new requirement we just have to change the &lt;code&gt;CalculateWithdrawalFee&lt;/code&gt; method &lt;b&gt;and&lt;/b&gt; add a new value in our &lt;code&gt;AccountType&lt;/code&gt; enum:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public enum AccountType
{
    Debit,
    Savings,
    Credit
}

...

private Money CalculateWithdrawalFee(Money amount)
{
    switch( _accountType )
	case AccountType.Savings:
	    return amount * 0.5 / 100;
	case AccountType.Credit:
	    return amount * 0.7 / 100;
	default:
	    return 0;
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The problem with this approach is that we had to add changes in more than one place; and the hint that this way of implementing the new requirement is not ok was given by the
&lt;i&gt;and&lt;/i&gt; conjunction from the previous sentence. And if that wasn't enough then the &lt;code&gt;switch&lt;/code&gt; should be the indicator of a possible code smell.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A better way to address these requirements is through inheritance by first determining which are the common traits of an &lt;code&gt;Account&lt;/code&gt; and extracting them into a base class followed by modeling the specific behavior for each
subsequent type of account into its separate class.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, as before, the common traits of an account are:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All accounts have a &lt;code&gt;Balance&lt;/code&gt; property
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All accounts support &lt;code&gt;Withdrawal&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Deposit&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All accounts validate available amount when a withdrawal is performed
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The distinct traits of the accounts are:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Savings accounts have a withdrawal fee of 0.5% of the amount withdrawn
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Credit accounts have a withdrawal fee of 0.7% of the amount withdrawn
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Debit accounts don't have a withdrawal fee
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Although we can see a clear difference between the common traits and specific features for each account type there is a certain amount of overlapping between them when performing a withdrawal.
In other words and specifically for withdrawal operation we can say that:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All account types support withdrawal
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each account type applies a specific withdrawal fee
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All account types validate the amount against available funds
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In order to model such kind of mixture between common and specific behavior we can make use of &lt;code&gt;polymorphism&lt;/code&gt; by defining an abstract method &lt;code&gt;CalculateWithdrawalFee&lt;/code&gt; which will be overridden
in the derived classes with specific values for each account type but still keeping the common behavior in a single place.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.codeproject.com/Articles/22769/Introduction-to-Object-Oriented-Programming-Concep#Polymorphism"&gt;Polymorphisms means the ability to request that the same operations be performed by a wide range of different types of things.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, with this approach let's address each requirement in the order they arrived. First, let's create the base class:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public abstract class Account
{
    public Money Balance { get; private set; }

    public void Deposit(Money money)
    {
	this.Balance += money;
    }

    public Money Withdraw(Money amount)
    {
	var fee = CalculateWithdrawalFee(amount);
	amount = amount + fee;
	if( Balance &amp;lt;= amount)
	{
	    throw new InvalidOperationException("Insufficient funds.");
	}
	this.Balance -= amount;
    }

    protected abstract Money CalculateWithdrawalFee(Money amount);
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With the base class in place, let's model the first two account types - &lt;i&gt;debit&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;savings&lt;/i&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class DebitAccount : Account
{
    protected override Money CalculateWithdrawalFee(Money amount)
    {
	return 0;
    }
}

public class SavingsAccount : Account
{
    protected override Money CalculateWithdrawalFee(Money amount)
    {
	return amount * 0.5 / 100;
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With this structure in place adding a new account type is as simple as adding a new derived class and all edits are in a single place - the newly added file:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class CreditAccount : Account
{
    protected override Money CalculateWithdrawalFee(Money amount)
    {
	return amount * 0.7 / 100;
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1-2" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sec-1-2"&gt;Chapter II - Structure&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How you structure your code is very important in software development. A good code structure promotes &lt;b&gt;low coupling and high cohesion&lt;/b&gt; which is a must for all good software.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's take a look at what &lt;b&gt;coupling&lt;/b&gt; and &lt;b&gt;cohesion&lt;/b&gt; mean.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1-2-1" class="outline-4"&gt;
&lt;h4 id="sec-1-2-1"&gt;Low coupling - The case of the &lt;code&gt;Singleton&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-4" id="text-1-2-1"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coupling_%2528computer_programming%2529"&gt;Coupling is the manner and degree of interdependence between software modules; a measure of how closely connected two routines or modules are; the strength of the relationships between modules.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To exemplify what &lt;b&gt;low coupling&lt;/b&gt; is and its importance let's take a look at the well-kown &lt;code&gt;Singleton&lt;/code&gt; pattern:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class FileSystem
{
    private static readonly FileSystem _root = new FileSystem();

    private FileSystem()
    {
    }

    public static FileSystem Root
    {
	get { return _root; }
    }

    public string[] List(string path)
    {
	return Directory.EnumerateDirectories(path)
	    .Union(Directory.EnumerateFiles(path))
	    .ToArray();
    }
}

public class Explorer
{
    public string CurrentDirectory { get; set; }

    public IEnumerable&amp;lt;string&amp;gt; Contents { get; private set;}

    public void NavigateTo(string path)
    {
	var contents = FileSystem.Root.List(path);
	CurrentDirectory = path;
	Contents = contents;

	foreach(var item in contents)
	{
	    Display(item);
	}
    }
}

public class Program
{
    static void Main(string[] args)
    {
	var explorer = new Explorer();
	explorer.NavigateTo(@"c:\users\petru\Documents\");
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What is wrong in the code above? &lt;b&gt;The &lt;code&gt;Explorer&lt;/code&gt; class is tightly coupled with &lt;code&gt;FileSystem&lt;/code&gt; singleton&lt;/b&gt;, i.e. &lt;code&gt;Explorer&lt;/code&gt; class is highly denendent on the &lt;code&gt;FileSystem&lt;/code&gt; class and cannot be used without the &lt;code&gt;FileSystem&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To demonstrate this &lt;b&gt;tight coupling&lt;/b&gt; let's create a test for &lt;code&gt;Explorer&lt;/code&gt; class to verify that it returns proper values from a known directory:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class ExplorerTests
{
    protected string Directory { get; set; }

    protected Explorer Explorer { get; private set;}

    protected void Initialize()
    {
	Explorer = new Explorer();
    }

    [TestClass]
    public class WhenNavigatingToTempDirectory : ExplorerTests
    {
	[TestInitialize]
	public void TestInitialize()
	{
	    Initialize();
	    Directory = @"C:\Temp\";
	}

	[TestMethod]
	public void ShouldDisplayDirectoryContents()
	{
	    Explorer.NavigateTo(Directory);
	    Assert.AreEqual(Directory, Explorer.CurrentDirectory);
	    Assert.AreEqual("C:\Temp\test.txt", Explorer.Contents.Single());
	}
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This test may succeed on our machine because we know that there's a file named &lt;code&gt;text.txt&lt;/code&gt; in our &lt;code&gt;C:\Temp\&lt;/code&gt; directory because we've put it there. But what if we execute that test on another machine? Will that file be there?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Having such code means that not only our &lt;code&gt;Explorer&lt;/code&gt; class is &lt;b&gt;tightly coupled&lt;/b&gt; with the &lt;code&gt;FileSystem&lt;/code&gt; class but also that this chain of dependency can grow to depend on the contents of the machine it's running on. We'll see how to break this dependecies in &lt;b&gt;Chapter III - SOLID code&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1-2-2" class="outline-4"&gt;
&lt;h4 id="sec-1-2-2"&gt;High cohesion - Why can't I have all code in &lt;code&gt;Program.cs&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-4" id="text-1-2-2"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cohesion_%2528computer_science%2529"&gt;Cohesion refers to the degree to which the elements of a module belong together.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The main reason for properly structuring your application is that &lt;b&gt;similar entities belong toghether&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's consider the previous example in a less cohesive form:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class Program
{
    static void Main(string[] args)
    {
	NavigateTo(@"C:\users\petru\Documents\");
    }

    static void NavigateTo(string path)
    {
	var contents = Directory.EnumerateDirectories(path)
	    .Union(Directory.EnumerateFiles(path));
	foreach(var item in contents)
	{
	    Display(item);
	}
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In this case our &lt;code&gt;Program&lt;/code&gt; is nothing more than a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/God_object"&gt;&lt;b&gt;God object&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - it does &lt;i&gt;everything&lt;/i&gt; and this is a problem. It may not be a problem for such a trivial application but when it comes to real applications things get more complicated.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Even small production applications have a lot of objects and that number keeps growing alongside the growth of the application and at some point having everything in one place is simply unbearable. Furthermore, chances are that more than one developer will be working on the same codebase and you can't just have everything in a single file.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1-3" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sec-1-3"&gt;Chapter III - SOLID code&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-3"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1-3-1" class="outline-4"&gt;
&lt;h4 id="sec-1-3-1"&gt;Single Responsibility Principle&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-4" id="text-1-3-1"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Single_responsibility_principle"&gt;Every module or class should have responsibility over a single part of the functionality provided by the software, and that responsibility should be entirely encapsulated by the class.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let's look again at our Account example:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public abstract class Account
{
    public Money Balance { get; private set; }

    public void Deposit(Money money)
    {
	this.Balance += money;
    }

    public Money Withdraw(Money amount)
    {
	var fee = CalculateWithdrawalFee(amount);
	amount = amount + fee;
	if( Balance &amp;lt;= amount)
	{
	    throw new InvalidOperationException("Insufficient funds.");
	}
	this.Balance -= amount;
    }

    protected abstract Money CalculateWithdrawalFee(Money amount);
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As you can see from the code, the &lt;code&gt;Withdraw&lt;/code&gt; method does more than one thing, namely:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It calculates the withdrawal fee
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It subtracts the amount and withdrawal fee from the balance
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The purpose of this method is to withdraw the &lt;code&gt;amount&lt;/code&gt; from the available balance; calculating the withdrawal fee should be someone else's responsibility. And that &lt;i&gt;someone else&lt;/i&gt; should be a &lt;code&gt;WithdrawalAmountCalculator&lt;/code&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class WithdrawalAmountCalculator
{
    public Money CalculateWithdrawalAmount(Money amount, decimal percentage)
    {
	return amount * percentage / 100;
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, let's put it all together and remove the extra responsibilities from &lt;code&gt;Account&lt;/code&gt; class:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class WithdrawalAmountCalculator
{
    public Money CalculateWithdrawalAmount(Money amount, decimal feePercentage)
    {
	return amount * feePercentage / 100;
    }
}

public abstract class Account
{
    private readonly WithdrawalAmountCalculator _amountCalculator;

    protected Account(WithdrawalFeeCalculator amountCalculator)
    {
	_amountCalculator = amountCalculator;
    }

    public Money Balance { get; private set; }

    public abstract decimal WithdrawalInterestRate { get; }

    public void Deposit(Money money)
    {
	this.Balance += money;
    }

    public Money Withdraw(Money amount)
    {
	var amountToWithdraw = _amountCalculator.CalculateWithdrawalAmount(amount, WithdrawalInterestRate);
	if( Balance &amp;lt;= amountToWithdraw)
	{
	    throw new InvalidOperationException("Insufficient funds.");
	}
	this.Balance -= amountToWithdraw;
	return amount;
    }
}

public class DebitAccount : Account
{
    public DebitAccount(WithdrawalAmountCalculator amountCalculator) : base(amountCalculator)
    {
    }

    public override decimal WithdrawalInterestRate
    {
	{ get { return 0m; }}
    }
}

public class Program
{
    static void Main(string[] args)
    {
	var calculator = new WithdrawalAmountCalculator();
	var account = new DebitAccount(calculator);
	account.Deposit(new Money(100));

	var cash = account.Withdraw(50);
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Much better! Each class does only one thing, namely:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;WithdrawalAmountCalculator&lt;/code&gt; calculates the withdrawal amount and
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Account&lt;/code&gt; handles the changes to balance.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1-3-2" class="outline-4"&gt;
&lt;h4 id="sec-1-3-2"&gt;Open/Closed principle&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-4" id="text-1-3-2"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open/closed_principle"&gt;Software entities (classes, modules, functions, etc.) should be open for extension, but closed for modification&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let's go back again to a previous example, the one with multiple account types:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public enum AccountType
{
    Debit,
    Savings,
    Credit
}

...

private Money CalculateWithdrawalFee(Money amount)
{
    switch( _accountType )
	case AccountType.Savings:
	    return amount * 0.5 / 100;
	case AccountType.Credit:
	    return amount * 0.7 / 100;
	default:
	    return 0;
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The code from the example above is the exact opposite of &lt;b&gt;Open/Closed principle&lt;/b&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is &lt;i&gt;open for modification&lt;/i&gt; because every time we'll need to create a new account type we'll have to add another &lt;code&gt;case&lt;/code&gt; to the &lt;code&gt;switch&lt;/code&gt; statement within &lt;code&gt;CalculateWithdrawalAmount&lt;/code&gt; method
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is &lt;i&gt;closed for extension&lt;/i&gt; in the sense that even if we do create a derived type of &lt;code&gt;Account&lt;/code&gt; that type will have to &lt;b&gt;always&lt;/b&gt; take into consideration the &lt;code&gt;AccountType&lt;/code&gt; property when implementing its custom behavior.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1-3-3" class="outline-4"&gt;
&lt;h4 id="sec-1-3-3"&gt;Liskov substitution principle&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-4" id="text-1-3-3"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liskov_substitution_principle"&gt;Objects in a program should be replaceable with instances of their subtypes without altering the correctness of that program.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To exemplify let's consider the overused &lt;code&gt;Rectangle&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Square&lt;/code&gt; example where one would model the relationship between them using the following statement: &lt;b&gt;a &lt;code&gt;Square&lt;/code&gt; is a &lt;code&gt;Rectangle&lt;/code&gt; having &lt;code&gt;Width == Height&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/b&gt; as behavioral description. In other words, &lt;i&gt;a &lt;code&gt;Square&lt;/code&gt; behaves exactly like a &lt;code&gt;Rectangle&lt;/code&gt; but the &lt;code&gt;Square&lt;/code&gt; has &lt;code&gt;Width == Heigth&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As an object hierarchy this would look like the following:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class Rectangle
{
    protected int _width;

    protected int _height;

    public virtual int Width
    {
	get { return _width; }
	set { _width = value; }
    }

    public virtual int Height
    {
	get { return _height; }
	set { _height = value; }
    }
}

public class Square : Rectangle
{
    public override int Width
    {
	get { return _width; }
	set
	{
	    _width = value;
	    _height = value;
	}
    }

    public override int Height
    {
	get { return _height; }
	set
	{
	    _height = value;
	    _width = value;
	}
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now let' think of consumer of this code: it knows it's working with a &lt;code&gt;Rectangle&lt;/code&gt; and sets all the values accordingly but it is given a &lt;code&gt;Square&lt;/code&gt; to work with. Let's see that in code:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class Program
{
    private const int ImageWidth = 800;
    private const int ImageHeight = 600;

    static void Main(string[] args)
    {
	var rectangle = new Square();
	InitializeRectangle(rectangle);
	var area = rectangle.Width * rectangle.Height;
	Debug.Assert(area == ImageWidth * ImageHeight);
    }

    void InitializeRectangle(Rectangle rectangle)
    {
	rectangle.Width = ImageWidth;
	rectangle.Height = ImageHeight;
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The method &lt;code&gt;InitializeRectangle&lt;/code&gt; will perform it's work on a &lt;code&gt;Rectangle&lt;/code&gt; thus will set its &lt;code&gt;Width&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Height&lt;/code&gt; properties and the &lt;code&gt;Main&lt;/code&gt; method will be expecting to have an rectangle with the area of &lt;code&gt;ImageWidth * ImageHeight&lt;/code&gt; but since the &lt;code&gt;Square&lt;/code&gt; overrides the &lt;code&gt;Width&lt;/code&gt; when &lt;code&gt;Height&lt;/code&gt; is set (and viceversa) the actual area of the rectangle will be &lt;code&gt;ImageHeight * ImageHeight&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This shows that although a &lt;code&gt;Square&lt;/code&gt; may have a similar structure with an &lt;code&gt;Rectangle&lt;/code&gt; it cannot be used as a substitute for a &lt;code&gt;Rectangle&lt;/code&gt; because it doesn't have the same behavior.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1-3-4" class="outline-4"&gt;
&lt;h4 id="sec-1-3-4"&gt;Interface Segregation principle&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-4" id="text-1-3-4"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interface_segregation_principle"&gt;Many client-specific interfaces are better than one general-purpose interface.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To exemplify this let's consider some existing types within &lt;code&gt;.NET Framework&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/system.web.security.membershipprovider%2528v=vs.110%2529.aspx"&gt;&lt;code&gt;MembershipProvider&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;code&gt;System.Web.Security&lt;/code&gt; namespace and &lt;a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dn613278%2528v=vs.108%2529.aspx"&gt;&lt;code&gt;IUserStore&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;code&gt;Microsoft.AspNet.Identity&lt;/code&gt; namespace:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public abstract class MembershipProvider : ProviderBase
{
    public abstract bool EnablePasswordRetrieval { get; }

    public abstract bool EnablePasswordReset { get; }

    public abstract bool RequiresQuestionAndAnswer { get; }

    public abstract string ApplicationName { get; set; }

    public abstract int MaxInvalidPasswordAttempts { get; }

    public abstract int PasswordAttemptWindow { get; }

    public abstract bool RequiresUniqueEmail { get; }

    public abstract MembershipPasswordFormat PasswordFormat { get; }

    public abstract int MinRequiredPasswordLength { get; }

    public abstract int MinRequiredNonAlphanumericCharacters { get; }

    public abstract string PasswordStrengthRegularExpression { get; }

    public event MembershipValidatePasswordEventHandler ValidatingPassword

    public abstract MembershipUser CreateUser(string username, string password, string email, string passwordQuestion, string passwordAnswer, bool isApproved, object providerUserKey, out MembershipCreateStatus status);

    public abstract bool ChangePasswordQuestionAndAnswer(string username, string password, string newPasswordQuestion, string newPasswordAnswer);

    public abstract string GetPassword(string username, string answer);

    public abstract bool ChangePassword(string username, string oldPassword, string newPassword);

    public abstract string ResetPassword(string username, string answer);

    public abstract void UpdateUser(MembershipUser user);

    public abstract bool ValidateUser(string username, string password);

    public abstract MembershipUser GetUser(object providerUserKey, bool userIsOnline);

    public abstract MembershipUser GetUser(string username, bool userIsOnline);

    internal MembershipUser GetUser(string username, bool userIsOnline, bool throwOnError)

    public abstract string GetUserNameByEmail(string email);

    public abstract bool DeleteUser(string username, bool deleteAllRelatedData);

    public abstract MembershipUserCollection GetAllUsers(int pageIndex, int pageSize, out int totalRecords);

    public abstract int GetNumberOfUsersOnline();

    public abstract MembershipUserCollection FindUsersByName(string usernameToMatch, int pageIndex, int pageSize, out int totalRecords);

    public abstract MembershipUserCollection FindUsersByEmail(string emailToMatch, int pageIndex, int pageSize, out int totalRecords);

    protected virtual byte[] EncryptPassword(byte[] password)

    protected virtual byte[] EncryptPassword(byte[] password, MembershipPasswordCompatibilityMode legacyPasswordCompatibilityMode)

    protected virtual byte[] DecryptPassword(byte[] encodedPassword)

    protected virtual void OnValidatingPassword(ValidatePasswordEventArgs e)

}


public interface IUserStore&amp;lt;TUser, in TKey&amp;gt; : IDisposable where TUser : class, IUser&amp;lt;TKey&amp;gt;
{
    Task CreateAsync(TUser user);

    Task UpdateAsync(TUser user);

    Task DeleteAsync(TUser user);

    Task&amp;lt;TUser&amp;gt; FindByIdAsync(TKey userId);

    Task&amp;lt;TUser&amp;gt; FindByNameAsync(string userName);
}

 public interface IUserPasswordStore&amp;lt;TUser, in TKey&amp;gt; : IUserStore&amp;lt;TUser, TKey&amp;gt;, IDisposable where TUser : class, IUser&amp;lt;TKey&amp;gt;
  {
    Task SetPasswordHashAsync(TUser user, string passwordHash);

    Task&amp;lt;string&amp;gt; GetPasswordHashAsync(TUser user);

    Task&amp;lt;bool&amp;gt; HasPasswordAsync(TUser user);
  }
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If we would have to implement a simple authentication mechanism the functionality of &lt;code&gt;IUserStore&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;IUserPasswordStore&lt;/code&gt; would be sufficient for our needs. Compare implementing only the functionality required for these two interfaces with the effort required to derive from the &lt;code&gt;MembershipProvider&lt;/code&gt; class. Even worse, I can say from my experience that with the &lt;code&gt;MembershipProvider&lt;/code&gt; you'll be writing code which will never be used.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1-3-5" class="outline-4"&gt;
&lt;h4 id="sec-1-3-5"&gt;Dependency Inversion principle&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-4" id="text-1-3-5"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dependency_inversion_principle"&gt;Depend upon Abstractions. Do not depend upon concretions.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let's go back to our &lt;code&gt;Singleton&lt;/code&gt; example. In the previous module we stated that the &lt;code&gt;Explorer&lt;/code&gt; class is &lt;b&gt;tightly coupled&lt;/b&gt; with the &lt;code&gt;FileSystem&lt;/code&gt; class thus depending on it and also depending on underlying file system for tests to succed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To break this dependency we need to hide the functionality of our &lt;code&gt;FileSystem&lt;/code&gt; behind an abstraction and we do that using an interface &lt;code&gt;IFileSystem&lt;/code&gt; which will be implemented by &lt;code&gt;FileSystem&lt;/code&gt; class:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public interface IFileSystem
{
    string[] List(string path);
}

public class FileSystem : IFileSystem
{
    public string[] List(string path)
    {
	return Directory.EnumerateDirectories(path)
	    .Union(Directory.EnumerateFiles(path))
	    .ToArray();
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now we make the &lt;code&gt;Explorer&lt;/code&gt; class depend upon the &lt;code&gt;IFileSystem&lt;/code&gt; interface:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class Explorer
{
    private readonly IFileSystem _fileSystem;

    public Explorer(IFileSystem fileSystem)
    {
	_fileSystem = fileSystem;
    }

    public string CurrentDirectory { get; set; }

    public IEnumerable&amp;lt;string&amp;gt; Contents { get; private set;}

    public void NavigateTo(string path)
    {
	var contents = _fileSystem.Root.List(path);
	CurrentDirectory = path;
	Contents = contents;

	foreach(var item in contents)
	{
	    Display(item);
	}
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now it's up to the &lt;code&gt;Program&lt;/code&gt; class to glue them together:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;public class Program
{
    static void Main(string[] args)
    {
	var fs = new FileSystem();
	var explorer = new Explorer(fs);
	explorer.NavigateTo(@"c:\users\petru\Documents\");
    }
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This way we can test the &lt;code&gt;Explorer&lt;/code&gt; class separately from the &lt;code&gt;FileSystem&lt;/code&gt; class by passing it an instance of a class that implements &lt;code&gt;IFileSystem&lt;/code&gt; and returns some stub data.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As an additional bonus, the semantics of the &lt;code&gt;Singleton&lt;/code&gt; is still in place - there is &lt;b&gt;only one instance&lt;/b&gt; of the &lt;code&gt;FileSystem&lt;/code&gt; class for the whole lifetime of the application.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cohesion</category><category>coupling</category><category>encapsulation</category><category>FII Practic</category><category>inheritance</category><category>OOP principles</category><category>polymorphism</category><category>presentation</category><category>programming principles</category><category>SOLID principles</category><guid>https://blog.rebeja.eu/posts/fii-practic-2016/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2016 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Welcome</title><link>https://blog.rebeja.eu/posts/welcome/</link><dc:creator>Petru Rebeja</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Welcome to my new and shiny blog!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here I'll be posting thoughts, stories and ideas from my everyday life as a developer.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you want to know the other (creative) part of me you can visit my other blog at &lt;a href="http://repierre.wordpress.com"&gt;http://repierre.wordpress.com&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Meanwhile checkout my activity on the following sites:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/users/844006/repierre"&gt;StackOverflow&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/petrurebeja"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ro.linkedin.com/in/petrurebeja"&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><guid>https://blog.rebeja.eu/posts/welcome/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2016 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>